בוקר טוב. Boker tov. We are in the middle of dealing with
issues around wine, both questions about what type of wine would you
still make a בורא פרי הגפן Borei Peri Hagefen if it starts
to go starting to go a little sour, it's smelling bad even
though it still tastes okay, and also the question about if you're
making wine by adding water to the lees, to the grape skins
and to the seeds and whatever, how much at what stage you
know when would that be considered when would you assume that there's
enough grape juice
in the water that that would be fit for making the ברכה
Bracha of בורא פרי הגפן. Borei Peri Hagefen. And every now and
then we also touch on some type of the direct concerns of
the פרק Perek which are some more business and נכסים ונפקות nechasim
venafkot type of issues. So we pick up with this on צ"ז
עמוד א'. Tzadi Zayin Amud Aleph. בעי מיני. Ba'ei Minei. It is
one, two, three, four, five, six lines from the top. בעי מיני
רב נחמן בר יצחק מרב חייא בר אבין. Ba'ei Minei Rav Nachman
Bar Yitzchak Me'Rav Chiya Bar Abin. רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman
Bar Yitzchak asked of רב חייא בר אבין: Rav Chiya Bar Abin:
שמרים Shemarim again these like lees שיש בהם טעם יין sheyesh bahem
ta'am yayin that they have still the taste of wine and presumably
it means that they're giving the taste of the wine to the
water that you added to them. מהו? Mahu? What's the הלכה? Halacha?
Okay presumably in a question about is it you know do you
make a ברכה Bracha because that's really the issue that we've been
focusing on, also question about would it be considered wine to be
obligated let's say maybe in תרומות ומעשרות terumos u'ma'asros but the issue
we've been more immediately focused or whatever to be considered מצה matza
but the issue we've been more directly focusing on is is the
ברכה. Bracha. So אמר ליה amar lei he said to him מי
סברת חמרא? mi savret chamra? Do you really think that's wine? קיוהא
בעלמא הוא. kiyu be'alma hu. That's just like you know a I
don't even know how to translate the word קיוהא kiyu like just
some type of a of like a aroma that's actually not the
wrong word some type of a how did they translate קיוהא kiyu
I should
have.
Acidulous liquid. It's what?
Acidula.
Acidulous?
I have no even idea that's fine. Sharp acidulated water flavor.
Yeah like a flavor flavor some type of a flavor that's not
real wine that's just some flavor of the grape that's not meaningful
at all. Now if he's talking about even the case that the
גמרא Gemara dealt with yesterday when you added three and then you
extracted four presumably not okay and the רשב"ם Rashbam assumes that the
discussions now in the גמרא Gemara was when you added water and
then you took out grapey water or grape-flavored water which is essentially
the same amount as the water you added. It's not a case
of adding three taking four. So in this type of a case
we basically already concluded yesterday that everybody would agree it's not wine
and that certainly explains his type of you know sort of like
you know exaggerated response. Ha! It's nothing! How can you call that
wine? You know but if it actually came out with a good
amount of extra liquid like then it wouldn't be so obvious. Yes.
So how important is the flavor in כשרות kashrus the standard today
is if there's any grape at all.
Correct. So I will get to that. תוספות Tosafot deals with that
issue about why don't we say normally you know if it's טרייף
treif stuff that's mixed up and there's some flavor then it's still
טרייף. treif. But just because there is some grape flavor in it
doesn't mean you can call it wine. You know if the wine
were something like you know let's say let's say the wine were
יין נסך yayin nesech or whatever the wine was really was טרייף
treif wine then yes a little bit of flavor is still a
problem because you know because there's טרייף treif wine in my water.
Right? There's a little טרייף treif wine that can still be tasted
in my food. It doesn't mean you call the water wine it
just means you say that there are traces of wine in the
food. But here the question is what do you call the water?
So he says the water is just you know grape-flavored water. The
water isn't wine. Okay? But your question will be more relevant in
a second. Okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. So our Rabbis taught. שמרים
של תרומה. Shemarim shel terumah. Now you have the lees of תרומה
terumah and now this was actually you know you had you had
grapes you took תרומה terumah from it you you know you gave
these grapes of תרומה terumah to the כהן Kohen let's say and
the כהן Kohen presses the grapes and makes wine from it and
then he adds water to these pressed you know grapes and is
going to make this grape-flavored water this תמד. temed. So will that
still have the קדושה kedusha of תרומה? terumah? Now that's more relevant
to Charlie's question because there you don't have to call the water
wine you just have to say the water has traces of תרומה
terumah grapes in it right? טעם כעיקר Ta'am ke'ikar and then it
should be maybe a problem. So the whole water wouldn't be considered
תרומה terumah but the question is can a non-כהן Kohen drink the
water
that you would say wait there's taste of תרומה terumah in the
water. It's not that you're calling the whole water wine. Okay that's
what you might have been inclined to say but right now the
גמרא Gemara is not going to bring up any of those standard
כשרות kashrus issues. It's going to look at it through the same
lens. Is this grape-flavored water considered wine or not or considered תרומה
terumah wine or not? So we'll get to your Charlie's question in
a minute תוספות Tosafot addresses it. שמרים של תרומה. Shemarim shel terumah.
Not that you're calling the whole water wine. Okay, that's what you
might have been inclined to say, but right now the גמרא Gemara
is not going to bring up any of those standard כשרות kashrus
issues, it's going to look at it through the same lens. Is
this grape flavored water considered wine or not? Or considered תרומה terumah
wine or not? So we'll get to the תוספות's Tosafos question in
a minute, תוספות Tosafos addresses it. שמרים של תרומה, Shmarim shel terumah,
ראשון ושני אסור, rishon v'sheini assur, ושלישי מותר. u'shlishi mutar. So you
had one, you had wine, you had water once to this barrel
with the lees in it and you take it out, that's considered
תרומה. terumah. You had water a second time and you take it
out, that's considered תרומה. terumah. The first two, you know,
mixers, mixes are תרומה. terumah. I know, it's totally parallels. I was
going to say that, the third one is already considered to be,
you know, there's such little of the of those grapes left in
the wine at the third stage that that's not תרומה. terumah. Okay,
now, as Michael correctly says, what you are going to see is
this directly parallels the טומאה וטהרה tuma v'tahara status. The basic story
is is that is that food people and vessels, אדם וכלי, adam
u'keili, can only be a ראשון rishon of טומאה. tumah. ראשון rishon
means one degree first degree derivative. So if they touch a let's
say a corpse of an animal, then and anything that touches it
is a ראשון. rishon. So anything can become a ראשון, rishon, even
people and כלים, keilim, but people and כלים keilim can only become
a ראשון. rishon. Let's say that person who's now a ראשון rishon
touches something else. That thing is a שני, sheini, two degrees derived.
The only thing that can become a שני sheini is food, okay.
Let's say now that שני sheini touches another piece of food. What
can become a שלישי? shlishi? So the only thing that can become
a שלישי shlishi is תרומה. terumah. Let's say a קודש kodesh can
be a רביעי. revi'i. Let's say, yeah I know right. Let's say
that שלישי shlishi touches another piece of food, can that piece of
food become tamei? The only thing that can become a רביעי revi'i
is קודש. kodesh. Okay, so basically, I mean the גמרא Gemara is
not going to make this comparison, but it's right there on the
surface so you have to make it. Okay, so basically, people and
vessels can only be a ראשון, rishon, okay, food can even become
a
שני, sheini, תרומה—here's terumah your dead
animal, okay, that's your נבלה neveilah corpse, okay, then how many degrees
derived, okay, תרומה terumah food, because obviously תרומה terumah is food, can
be a שלישי, shlishi, okay, and קודש kodesh food can become a
רביעי. revi'i.
Okay,
so that's the, right? But תרומה terumah cannot be a רביעי, revi'i,
people cannot be a שני sheini etc. So anyway this roughly parallels
that.
Right,
exactly, food can't be a ראשון, rishon, תרומה terumah can be a
ראשון, rishon, right, exactly. Okay, so this is sort of like this
one removed. שמרים של תרומה, Shmarim shel terumah, ראשון ושני אסור, rishon
v'sheini assur, you know, it's the first and second derivative of תרומה
terumah can still be the you know, which means third, right? Because
this
was the original wine, okay, then you had תמד temed number one,
you know, and then you had תמד temed number two, and all
of those if you're dealing with תרומה, terumah, all of those are
considered תרומה. terumah. So it's sort of like you know what I
mean, it's sort of like three stages. So and then the next
stage is not. So it's sort of like this minus one, because
it's the first and second stage of תמד temed is already one
degree removed. Anyway, it directly—you can look at the list, I'm not
going to keep on referring to it because it's not in the
גמרא, Gemara, but it sort of directly parallels that. Okay, שמרים של
תרומה, Shmarim shel terumah, ראשון ושני אסור. rishon v'sheini assur. The first
and second grapey water of תרומה terumah is considered תרומה, terumah, ובשלישי
מותר, u'v'shlishi mutar, the third one is already permissible. רבי מאיר אומר
אף שלישי נותן טעם. Rabbi Meir omer af shlishi nosein ta'am. No,
even the third one, if it still has some taste of wine
in it, some taste of grape in it, it's still forbidden. Now
actually, as we were saying before, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir makes complete
sense, because you don't have to consider this grapey water wine, you
just have to say if there's traces of תרומה terumah in the
water, then you have to treat it like תרומה. terumah. Okay, you
don't have to consider the whole water wine, which sounds like what
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is saying is that if there's just taste,
there's taste. So the גמרא Gemara never really directly addresses that question.
תוספות Tosafos does. If you look at תוספות, Tosafos, תוספות Tosafos says
like this, אמאי קרי ליה הכי פטרוה אבא דם ברמת תלתא ואתא
תלתא פלגא כיון דאית ביה נותן טעם דקיימא לן פרק בתרא דעבודה
זרה דמין בשאינו מינו בנותן טעם כדי תבל.
amai karei lei hachi patrui abba dam beramat tlata v'ata tlata palga
keivan d'is bei nosein ta'am d'kayma lan perek basra d'Avodah Zarah d'min
b'sheino
mino b'nosein ta'am k'dei tevel. So he asks it on the previous
סוגיא. sugya. There's an easier answer because the previous סוגיא sugya was
talking about the definition of wine.
This you just have to say for to be תרומה terumah there
just has to be taste of תרומה terumah in the water. Anyway,
let's see his answer. ויש לומר דאינו אלא קיוהא בעלמא, V'yesh lomar
d'eino ela kiyuha b'alma, like the גמרא Gemara says, אין כאן נותן
טעם, ein kan nosein ta'am, וכעפרא בעלמא דמי. u'k'afra b'alma dami. That
basically what you say is, and it's a funny idea, but what
you say is, yeah, that fact that the grape leaves are giving
some grapey taste is not actually, you know, it's like taste that—it's
a funny idea because normally the whole point is that we say
that טעם ta'am represents the thing itself. But here you're basically saying
that you're not really getting any grape juice that's mixing up, somehow
by their contact with... The grape leaves are getting some taste of
wine, but it's almost like you're getting the taste without the actual
thing itself. It sounds like what he's saying. It's still a funny
idea because normally we have a הלכה halakhic word for that, it's
called טעמו ולא ממשו, ta'amo velo mamasho, that you can get the
taste without the transfer of the thing itself and it's still considered
a problem. You know, it's almost like תוספות Tosafot is saying it's
like, you know, it's sort of like bacon, bacon bits, you know,
fake bacon bits. It tastes like bacon, but it's not, it's not
a problem of טעם ta'am bacon because it's not real bacon. Okay.
So, but the problem is, this doesn't just taste like wine, it
came from grapes, you know? So it is a funny idea, although
there are other places where the גמרא Gemara discusses this. Like the
גמרא Gemara discusses like juice that runs off of fish, you know,
ציר, tziyar, is that considered to be like, and it's a טריפה
treif fish. Is that considered to be טריפה treif as well and
it needs special, and maybe it's just considered to be like the
dross of the thing, not the fish itself. So it's a funny
idea that the גמרא Gemara never really fully addresses and even תוספות
Tosafot is not fully clear. But yes, this is a funny idea.
Here we're not just saying that the stuff isn't wine, we're somehow
saying we don't even have to care about the wine flavor in
it, it's not considered real wine.
Maybe you need more מחמיר machmir for these kind of...
what? I don't know. Anyway, but, but רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir position
makes a lot of sense. The גמרא Gemara never fully addresses it,
but it is a shift from the question of, is this mixture
wine, to do we have to be considered about the traces of
wine in this mixture? And it's pretty interesting that it seems like
we don't. Okay. ושל מעשר, u-shel ma'aser, now let's say it's מעשר,
ma'aser, מעשר שני, ma'aser sheni, because מעשר ראשון ma'aser rishon or מעשר
עני ma'aser ani does not have any הלכה halakhic status. I mean,
it's owned by the כהן kohen or the עני, ani, but here
we're talking about מעשר שני ma'aser sheni that has קדושה, kedusha, that
has to be in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. ראשון אסור שני מותר. rishon asur
sheni mutar. In that case, the first grapey water is forbidden, has
the status, the second is permissible.
רבי מאיר אומר אף שני בנותן טעם. Rabbi Meir omer af sheni
benoten ta'am. Even the second one, if it's got taste, it has
that status. ושל הקדש, ve-shel hekdesh, now if it's הקדש, hekdesh, so
again following that chart, it's one degree further than תרומה. terumah. שלישי
אסור, shelishi asur, even the third batch of grapey water is forbidden,
has the status of תרומה. terumah. רביעי מותר, revi'i mutar, the fourth
one is permissible. רבי מאיר אומר אף רביעי בנותן טעם. Rabbi Meir
omer af revi'i benoten ta'am. No, even the fourth one if it
still has the taste. Okay.
Does he say also the fifth
one if it has a taste? Yeah, that's not clear. Okay. ורמינהו,
u-raminhu, I'll ask you on this. And by the way, and the
רשבם Rashbam says all of this is when he put in the
water and you took out the same amount of water. So there's
really no concern of any real grape juice in the water, right?
So that helps explaining this. Somehow you say it got the flavor
or the taste without getting any of the real juice into it.
Okay. ורמינהו, u-raminhu, I'll ask you on this.
של הקדש, shel hekdesh, I'll give you another example maybe that helps
understands this, again it's not exactly the same, but there's a whole
discussion in the גמרא Gemara actually it ties into a גמרא Gemara
we just did before about whether ריחא מילתא. rei'a milta. Okay, this
is actually all relevant questions about ovens and how much do you
need, you know, to cook things separately in ovens and so on.
So the גמרא Gemara deals with a question of, here I am,
I'm, you know, having a barbecue, I'm frying some, I don't know,
some nice delicious steak and hamburger, I can smell it, it's delicious,
whatever, okay, and right next by, right near it, I've got, I
don't know, a piece of cheese. It never touches it, never, it's
on a table two feet away or whatever it is, maybe it's
under the same awning so that the things touch but never touches,
and now I bite into the cheese and it actually has absorbed
some of that smell of the barbecue. So according to one opinion
of the גמרא, Gemara, ריחא לאו מילתא היא, rei'a lav milta hi,
it's totally fine, even though it's obviously some meat flavor transferred via
smell to the cheese, but הלכה halakhically we say the smell meant
nothing. So therefore even though it's got some meat flavor it's nothing.
So that seems to be a similar idea that we're dealing with
here. If you put in water and you took out the same
amount, then we're going to say it's got no grape juice into
it, maybe somehow it got some of that flavor, but that flavor's
meaningless. Anyway, but moving on. Okay, so that's the case that we're
dealing with here. And then based on whether you're dealing with תרומה
terumah or מעשר ma'aser or whatever, or קודש, kodesh, we will have
different degrees of stringency when we will still consider it to be
a problem, you know, first batch, second batch, third batch. And the
רשבם Rashbam says that all of this is just a חומרא, humra,
a stringency, because in principle none of this is a problem because
it's the same amount of water you extracted, but different stringencies based
on what type of prohibition or what type of status we're talking
about. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: ורמינהו, u-raminhu, I'll
ask you on this. של הקדש לעולם אסור. shel hekdesh le-olam asur.
We have a ברייתא baraita that goes further by הקדש hekdesh and
not as far by מעשר. ma'aser. הקדש, hekdesh, no matter how many
batches, it's always going to be a problem. ושל מעשר, u-shel ma'aser,
and if it's מעשר, ma'aser, again presumably מעשר שני, ma'aser sheni, לעולם
מותר. le-olam mutar. Even the first batch is not a problem. So
it's more lenient by מעשר ma'aser and more strict by הקדש. hekdesh.
So of course you could always say it's a debate, but
קשיא הקדש אהקדש קשיא מעשר אמעשר. kashya hekdesh a-hekdesh kashya ma'aser a-ma'aser.
There's a contradiction about their positions about הקדש hekdesh and מעשר. ma'aser.
הקדש אהקדש לא קשיא. hekdesh a-hekdesh lo kashya. No, no, הקדש hekdesh
isn't a problem. כאן בקדושת הגוף כאן בקדושת דמים. kan bi-kdushat ha-guf
kan bi-kdushat damim. Are you just saying I'm donating the
wine for its money value to the בית המקדש, Beit ha-Mikdash, let
them sell it and use the proceeds?
A certain degree of stringency. But if you say I'm donating the
wine here or the grapes whatever to be used, to be pressed
in order to make יין yayin on the מזבח, mizbeiach, to be
used as a קרבן korban on the מזבח mizbeiach as part of
the קרבנות, korbanot, you know, you bring wine and so on, that's
considered to be a much weightier type of a קדושה kedusha and
therefore we would be strict even, you know, in multiple derivatives of
that עד העולם ad ha-olam forever. Okay, so that's the resolution of
הקדש. hekdesh. מעשר מעשר נמי לא קשיא. maiser maiser nami lo kashya.
Why are we, what's the difference between the מעשר maiser positions? כאן
במעשר ודאי כאן במעשר דמאי. kan be-maiser vadai kan be-maiser demai. When
we say מעשר maiser has one batch it's still a problem, that's
when it's definitely מעשר. maiser. When we say מעשר maiser even the
first batch is not a problem, that's when it's מעשר maiser taken
from דמאי. demai. דמאי demai is grain that you buy from the
עמי הארץ amei ha-aretz which are the farmers who are not, you
know, super scrupulous by תרומות ומעשרות trumos u-maasros and therefore, you buy
תרומות trumos they are, מעשר maiser they're not, anyway, therefore you have
to separate it because maybe it already had תרומות ומעשרות trumos u-maasros
separated, maybe not. So you do it, so the rabbis required you.
But because it's not definitely מעשר, maiser, you know, it's מעשר maiser
of דמאי, demai, we should be more lenient and even the first
batch is not a problem. Okay, so that's the end of that
discussion about the multiple batches and when does it, is it still
considered A yesterday, when is it still considered wine? And here B,
we're doing like we said a something that sounds like a more
כשרות kashrus issue but the גמרא gemara seems not so concerned with
it which is when are we still concerned with the with the
traces of the wine in it and it basically seems in principle
we're not and it's just these various degrees of stringency. Okay, so
now the גמרא gemara says like this, אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי
שמעון בן יהוצדק. amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon ben Yehotzadak. So
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said in the name of רבי שמעון בן
יהוצדק Rabbi Shimon ben Yehotzadak כשם שאמרו במעשר כשם שאמרו לענין איסורין.
keshem she-amru be-maiser keshem she-amru l'inyan issurin. In the same way we
said by איסור, issur, meaning איסור issur means like the status, is
the תרומה truma status first still in this first batch of the
grapey water of this תמד? temed? Is it in the second batch?
Is it in the third batch? The same way we had those
questions about the status of this תמד temed of this grapey water,
כך אמרו לענין הכשירן. kach amru l'inyan hechsharan. The same is true
about whether these liquids are considered to be wine or water when
it comes to the question of can it be מכשיר machshir food?
So מכשיר machshir food is you take food, you know, you pick
an apple off a tree, obviously it rained on the apple and
on the tree as it was growing but that has no הלכה
halacha meaning until you pick the apple. Now the apple's picked, it's
food and it can become טמא. tamei. But it can't become טמא,
tamei, food cannot become טמא tamei until actually it comes in contact
with a liquid. Whether it's wine or water, I know, thank you,
that's what the גמרא gemara has. So the point is like this.
The גמרא gemara says well, let's say it came in contact with
this grapey water. Okay, so will that make it מכשיר, machshir, make
it fit for becoming טמא? tamei? So the same debate we have
before at what batch is water and what batch, you know, what
batch it is considered wine and when would it be considered no
longer wine and just water, that would be relevant here too whether
it can make the food טמא. tamei. So if it was תרומה
truma up to the third batch was considered, the second batch was
considered wine and at the third batch water if you were dealing
with this grapey water, you know, if it was הקדש hekdesh of
the third batch would still be wine the fourth batch water and
that would be relevant if you're using now this grapey הקדש hekdesh
water or this grapey תרומה truma water and it came in contact
with an apple to know whether the apple is going to be
fit for becoming טמא, tamei, did it come in contact with water
or with wine? So the גמרא gemara says who cares? Both water
and wine are liquids that can make food fit for becoming טמא.
tamei. So that's what the גמרא gemara says. So the גמרא gemara
says הכשירן דמאי, hechsharan demai, what are we talking about? Not the
דמאי demai of before, of what? Okay?
אי דמיא, ei damya, if it's considered water, אכשורי מכשרי. achshurei machshiri.
So okay, water also is מכשיר. machshir. אי דחמרא, ei dechamra, and
if it was an early batch where it's considered wine, and notice
again the גמרא gemara is now saying that the early batches are
considered a form of wine, not water with wine traces, but a
form of wine. If it's considered to be wine, אכשורי מכשרי, achshurei
machshiri, then also is מכשיר. machshir. So who cares whether it's wine
or water has relevance not just for its תרומה truma status but
also for coming in contact with the apple. Who cares? Water or
wine, same difference. So the גמרא gemara says לא צריכה שתמדו במי
גשמים. lo tzricha she-temado be-mei geshamim. That what you did is here
you have your barrel,
here's
your barrel and here are the lees at the bottom of the
barrel and here you are and, you know, you've got let's say
a bucket here and it's raining into the bucket. Okay, and then
you pour the bucket into there. Now why is that relevant? Because
since it's rain water, rain water is not מקבל טומאה mekabel tumah
until you decide that you want it, that you want to use
it. Okay? And therefore the גמרא gemara says that since we're dealing
with rain water you have to want to use it. So if
it's wine presumably and תוספות Tosafos doesn't know why the גמרא gemara
is assuming this but if it's wine. Since it's wine, the גמרא's
Gemara assuming, wine automatically is מכשיר, machshir, makes it susceptible, whether you've
decided you are interested in the wine or not interested in the
wine, you know, I don't know, let's say some accident happened. A
grape fell off of a tree and something fell on it and
grape juice came out, it doesn't matter and then it hit an
apple lying on the ground. You don't have to know about it,
care about it, the very just fact that grape juice or wine,
you know, came in contact with it, that is מכשיר. machshir. Wine
would also be grape juice, yeah I'm saying grape juice, I should
be saying wine, but the point is here it's, you know, it's
not yet obviously just, you know, it's just it hasn't fermented. Okay?
So wine is, so you know, but I'll say wine just so
it's to be clear. So wine is מכשיר machshir whether you want
it or not want it or whatever, you're aware of it, not
aware of it, etc. And the assumption is that water, as for
whatever reason we're assuming that, water as we know from many other
sources, it has to be לרצון, le-ratzon, it's only if you sort
of either want the water or want the water to be on
the fruit or so on. So therefore, the case is you used
water that was just סתם stam rain water. So you haven't yet
signified that you care about the water. So if in the first
few batches where it's wine it'll be מכשיר, machshir, just the physical
reality that wine came in contact. But by the batches that it's
just water, that won't be מכשיר machshir unless you've demonstrated your
desire and your רצון.
ratzon. So is it water or wine?
Exactly. So now תוספות Tosafot says we've never heard anywhere that this
requirement of being מכשיר, machshir, this requirement that it be לרצון, le-ratzon,
you know, and that you want it on the fruit or you
want the thing, makes a difference if it's water or wine. So
תוספות Tosafot is really grapples with why the גמרא Gemara assumes here
there should be any halakhic difference between the two, but we're just
going to work with that for now. Okay, so it says like
this. So the גמרא Gemara says בשתמתא דמי גשמים. beshitmata de-mei geshamim.
So since it's rain water and it's not water you drew from
the well, it's just rain water. If you drew it from the
well, you've demonstrated your desire for it. So of course everything would
be מכשיר, machshir, water or wine. But if it was just rain
water and you never sort of like, you know, drew it, it
just fell. So in that type of a case, so you haven't
demonstrated your desire for it. As wine it's מכשיר, machshir, as rain
water it's not. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, וכיון דקא
שקיל ורמי ליה למנא אחשביה. ve-kivan de-ka shakil ve-rami lei le-mana, achshivei.
Okay,
what do I care? So you didn't draw it from the well.
But it fell into your bucket. And then you took the rain
water in your bucket and you put it into the barrel with
the grape lees in it. So that shows you want the water.
Okay, so who cares if it's rain water? You've already demonstrated your
desire for it. So the גמרא Gemara says לא צריכא שנתמד מאליה.
lo tzricha she-nitmad me-eila.
No, no, no, it didn't fall in your bucket and from there
go into the water. The rain water fell straight into your barrel,
okay? So your barrel happened to have been left open after you
took out all the wine and there was the gook at the
bottom and happened to have been left open and, you know, then
rain fell in it, you weren't even thinking about it, planning for
it or whatever. And then, and then apparently it started spilling out,
somehow it got tipped over, who knows what happened, a
lot of rain so it overflowed.
Or maybe it overflowed, right, that's a good point, that would be
a better way in which it happened, and then it came out.
Okay, so in that type of a case, you haven't demonstrated your
desire for it. The first few batches are wine and are מכשיר
machshir even without demonstrated desire and but once it's the batch that's
considered water, it's only מכשיר machshir when you demonstrate your desire. So
the גמרא Gemara says one minute, דכיון דקא נגיד קמא קמא אחשביה.
de-kivan de-ka nagid kama kama, achshivei. So
the גמרא Gemara first assumes that one minute what's hap- how did
this barrel get empty? This barrel must have got empty because you
saw it filled and you poured it out and emptied it out
and then, you know, put it and then stood it back up
or whatever. So the fact that you're pouring it out and extracting
now this תמד tamed from it shows that you want the תמד.
tamed. So again it shouldn't matter. What do you mean maybe you're
just trying to clean the barrel? You don't want to because it's
making a mess. I guess the גמרא Gemara could have said that.
Okay, but anyway, but this is what, but anyway, but that's the
way the גמרא, Gemara, but then you also wound up leaving the
lees on the bottom. Okay, anyway, the גמרא Gemara says but isn't
the taking the water out showing that you want it? So the
גמרא Gemara says no, אמר רב פפא בפרה דשתת ראשון ראשון. Amar
Rav Papa be-para she-shota rishon rishon. So
it's not that you're taking the water out, some cow is drinking
it and again not exactly sure is it rain water? And because
the cow is drinking it, then because if the cow didn't drink
it, if it was just constantly was raining, you know, then you
wouldn't have a first batch, a second batch, and a third batch.
How would you define different batches? It's just constantly raining. So you
have to have- you have to have different periods of rain. First
it rained, then a cow came along and drank it. I don't
know if it knocked it over and drank it or stuck its
head in and drank it. Okay, and therefore then it rained some
more, that was the second batch, and then it rained, so each
time you haven't done anything. Everything just happened in nature by itself.
And therefore you have never demonstrated any רצון. ratzon. So the first
few batches which are wine are considered halakhically wine so it's מעשר
maaser or טבל tevel or תרומה terumah whatever, that would have הלכה
halakha for, that would be even without demonstrating desire, right? And the
third one would only and when it's got to be water, it's
only מכשיר machshir when you demonstrate your desire. water, it would only
be an issue when you demonstrated your desire for it. Anyway, but
all of this is, as the רשב"ם Rashbam says, all of these
are חומרות. chumros. In principle, this is all just considered water, it's
not considered wine, and therefore we can have different levels of stringency
based on תרומה terumah and מעשר maaser and קודש kodesh and so
on. Okay, but basically, you know, as we said before, when the
same amount of liquid is extracted as was put in, it's considered,
it's not considered wine. One final thing about this before we get
onto the next point. Look at this, I always like these ריאליה
realia of תוספות. Tosafot. Look at this תוספות Tosafot מיסב Misav and
חמרא chamra הוא hu כמיא k'maya בעלמא be'alma הוא. hu. So he
says, it's the little תוספות Tosafot there, second תוספות Tosafot on the
top. He says, מכאן mikan הורה hora רבינו Rabbeinu תם Tam בדיעבד
bidiavad אם im רחץ rachatz עכו"ם akum חבית chavit של shel שמרי
shimrei
יין yayin דשרי. dishari. So you have, you're dealing with your wine,
right? There's a problem about a non-Jew touching the wine, making it
סתם יינם, stam yeinam. you know, and he goes ahead and he's
one of your workers or whatever, you got to be careful, where
do your non-Jewish workers work in your vineyard? Anyway, he came afterwards
and he washed out the barrel of the, you know, from the
lees at the bottom. So apparently the question is, well if the
water plus the lees at the bottom make wine and he's washing
it out and he's touching it, then maybe some of that gets
back into the barrel, like it's not exactly clear, but there'd be
some concern about some of that water, you know, that got mixed
with lees that he even touched it. So is it a סתם
יינם Stam yeinam issue that you've found? Yeah, so it's a little
question like what's תוספות Tosafot exactly bothered with, like where did that
water go? Why, why are you concerned with that water? But somehow
he was concerned with where that water was going to go.
But some other halachic issues that you've found it becomes a problem?
No, not just סתם stam there, it would have to be there
long enough to absorb. So it's not exactly clear what's bothering תוספות.
Tosafot. Who knows, maybe he does it like, you ever know on
a מוצאי motzaei שבת Shabbat you take the טשולנט cholent pot and
you put it with water and you let it wait 24 hours?
That's always a good excuse if you're tired of doing dishes. No,
no, no, the pot has to sit a little bit. Anyway, so
I don't know, whatever it was, if he touched this water, okay,
תוספות Tosafot says, דלאו dilav חמרא chamra הוא hu אלא ela כמיא
k'maya בעלמא be'alma הוא, hu, we don't have to worry that he
touched it, it's not considered wine, okay.
And was it an issue of ברכה bracha or
was it an issue of כשרות? kashrut? What? I know, but תוספות
Tosafot is assuming that there's a basic, a consistent question of whether
we consider it to be wine or not. Okay, so now back
to the גמרא. Gemara. Now we get to something that is very
למעשה. lemaaseh. אמר amar רב Rav זוטרא Zutra בר bar טוביה Tuvia
אמר amar רב Rav אין ein אומרים omerim קידוש kiddush היום hayom
אלא ela על al היין hayayin הראוי harauy לנסך lenasech על al
גבי gabei המזבח. hamizbeach.
You can only say קידוש kiddush on wine, אגב agav מזבח, mizbeach,
you can only say קידוש kiddush on wine that you can pour
to be, you know, one of the wines that could be brought
together with a קרבן korban on the מזבח. mizbeach. So first of
all, before we get to הלכהly halacha what does that mean, what's
the point of the comparison? Right, you know. So the רשב"ם Rashbam
just says it means that it has to be really nice, because
one of the requirements of everything you bring as a קרבן korban
is, you know, is that it has to be like in a,
aesthetically nice, you know, it has to be like top quality. There's
a פסוק pasuk says, you know, there's a פסוק pasuk by מלאכי,
Malachi, right? It says, הקריבהו נא לפחתך Hakrivehu na lefachatecha, הירצך או
הישא פניך, Hayirtzecha o hayissa panecha?
you take a קרבן korban that's like not perfect, would you bring
that to like an honored person? Would that find, would you know,
would that be something that would find favor in somebody else's eyes?
So when you bring something to God, it has to be like
top quality. So the רשב"ם Rashbam says that's the only point. The
point of the analogy of the comparison just before we get to
the הלכה halacha translation is that you want to use something not
just to make בורא פרי הגפן, borei pri hagafen, and here's part
of the point, right? The point of this statement is there are
things you could say בורא פרי הגפן Borei pri ha-gefen? on, בורא
פרי הגפן Borei pri ha-gefen. was the previous discussion, there are things
you could say בורא פרי הגפן Borei pri ha-gefen on, but they're
not fit for קידוש, kiddush, the same way they're not fit for
a, for the מזבח. mizbeach. And so the רשב"ם, Rashbam, the point
is because they're not good enough quality. But I still think that
the analogy suggests more than that, you know, the idea about like,
like when you had the בית Beis המקדש, HaMikdash, you know, there
was like the sacral, I guess that's the word, you know, or
sacred eating was what took place in the context of the בית
Beis המקדש. HaMikdash. Well it took place with תרומה terumah and מעשר,
maaser, right? But it took place, I mean, with תרומה, terumah, let's
say, was a type of a sacred food and sacred eating, but
more broadly for the, for everybody, it took place when you bring
a קרבן. korban. A, even if you don't eat the קרבן, korban,
only the כהנים Kohanim do, at least you provided the food for
the מזבח mizbeach and for the כהנים. Kohanim. And if it's a
שלמים, shlamim, then you participate in it. Even if it's an עולה,
olah, it's God's food. So the whole idea of like sacred food
and sacred eating. And then the question is, post-חורבן, churban,
how do we maintain that? So one way is of course ברכות,
brachot, right? You make a ברכה bracha and the גמרא Gemara says
if you don't make a ברכה bracha it's כאילו ke'ilu מעל. maal.
Although that's a little ironic, because then the ברכה bracha is like
taking it out of being קודש kodesh and making it desacralized, almost.
But nevertheless, it brings a sanctity to the act. Washing hands before
bread is because you would wash hands before תרומה, terumah, right? And
since every meal fundamentally has, the staple of every meal would be
bread, right? So that would also make it a type of a
תרומה. terumah. So now there are some meals that are particularly holy,
קידוש, kiddush, קדוש, kadosh, right? So the קידוש kiddush for, you know,
for the שבת Shabbat meal and the קידוש kiddush could be seen
as framing the entire meal, which is why אין ein קידוש kiddush
אלא ela במקום bimkom סעודה, seuda, right? Because it sort of gives
a framing to the... the whole meal. So therefore like to be
making this analogy that this is now like the wine you bring
on the מזבח, mizbeach, right,
is I think that there's a sort of a power to that
analogy. And I'm sure when we were all growing up, our mothers
told us don't sit on the table, the table is
דומיא דמזבח, dumya demizbeach, and all those types of things. So anyway,
it's all sort of it's connected. But I think that that's an
important, very important to appreciate the analogy before we get to the
halachic translation. Yes,
Michael? Right. So one could have taken it to a different end,
that then therefore you can't even use יין מבושל yayin mevushal because
of...
We're going to get to that. Don't worry, we're going to get
to all that. Okay, so you're already into הלכה. halacha. Okay, moving
on. So now the גמרא Gemara says, so now let the גמרא
Gemara get into הלכה. halacha. למעוטי מאי? Lema'utei mai? What type of
wine are you excluding? And again, with the presumption that it's wine
that you would say בורא פרי הגפן, Borei pri ha-gefen but not
wine that you could use for קידוש. kiddush. אילימא למעוטי יין מגיתו?
Eilima lema'utei yayin migito? Here, a very relevant for the grape juice
issue comes up today. Wine straight out of the pressing house, pressing
floor,
which is, it's, I mean, it hasn't fermented. Now, it's not grape
juice because it's yet unfermented wine. Grape juice can't ferment. They pasteurize
it, they do things, we'll get to that. Okay, but this is
wine that is one day old. You
squeeze the grapes. Okay, that's what it is. So we would call
it grape juice. It's unfermented wine. So and that may be because
and that's not good, because it's the רשב"ם Rashbam quotes the פסוק,
pasuk, הסך נסך שכר. hasech nesech shechar.
So the word שכר, shechar, which it refers to, is לשכר. leshacher.
It has to be intoxicating, so it has to be fermented. והא
תני רבי חייא, Veha tani Rabbi Chiya, יין מגיתו לא יביא, yayin
migito lo yavi, לכתחילה lechatchila
you shouldn't bring it, because you require at least לכתחילה שכר, lechatchila
shechar, יין שכר, yayin shechar, נסך שכר. nesech shechar. ואם הביא כשר.
Ve'im heivi kasher. So you can use grape juice on the מזבח,
mizbeach, what we just said? What? Oh, you can use unfermented wine.
Unfermented wine you can use on the מזבח. mizbeach. Okay, now, so
maybe, but maybe we should also say that therefore it should be
בדיעבד bedieved for קידוש. kiddush. So the גמרא Gemara maybe immediately that's
the point, fine, at least the point is לכתחילה lechatchila don't use
it. So the גמרא Gemara says, no. וכיון דאם הביא כשר, Vecheivan
de'im heivi kasher, if it's true that on the מזבח mizbeach it's
בדיעבד כשר, bedieved kasher, אנן אפילו לכתחילה נמי. anan afilu lechatchila nami.
We're not going to go so far to say we're going to
have the exact same standard. If something is בדיעבד bedieved good on
the מזבח, mizbeach, then it'll be even לכתחילה lechatchila good for us
for wine for קידוש. kiddush. So, yeah, Michael, too bad, you're going
to miss out the whole discussion of מבושל mevushal and grape juice
and so on. It's all coming up. Wait, wait, let's get a
little further. So that's important. The גמרא Gemara is saying we're not
taking the comparison עד הסוף. ad hasof. We're not going to translate
a לכתחילה lechatchila to making a demand by קידוש. kiddush. We will
translate something that's פסול בדיעבד pasul bedieved on the מזבח mizbeach to
making a demand by קידוש. kiddush. So here, by the way, the
גמרא Gemara says unfermented wine לכתחילה lechatchila you could use for קידוש,
kiddush, meaning again, there could still be a מצוה מן המובחר, mitzvah
min hamuvchar, but it's not considered בדיעבד. bedieved.
And that you would think would translate into grape juice as well,
but we will get to the grape juice discussion, our contemporary grape
juice in a minute.
Okay? Now דאמר רבא, de'amar Rava, or some have ואמר רבא, ve'amar
Rava, and I'll show you it's even לכתחילה. lechatchila. סוחט אדם אשכול
של ענבים, Socheit adam eshkol shel anavim,
take yourself a cluster of grapes, squeeze it out, ואומר עליו קידוש
היום. ve'omer alav kiddush hayom. But I have an advice, don't squeeze
it on שבת, Shabbos, okay? Which is a מלאכה melacha on שבת.
Shabbos.
So squeeze it on ערב שבת erev Shabbos and then once you
get the grape juice, then you could make קידוש kiddush and then
you could say, and then you could make it into שבת. Shabbos.
Okay, so that's even לכתחילה, lechatchila, unfermented wine.
ואלא למעוטי מפיה ומשוליה? Ve'ela lema'utei mipeha umishuleha? How about wine from
the top of the barrel and the bottom? That is less than,
that's less than pure filtered wine. The bottom has some of the
lees mixed up in it and the top has some dust or
whatever because it's been exposed. Okay, so maybe that's like סוג ב
sug beis wine. והא תני רבי חייא, Veha tani Rabbi Chiya, doesn't
רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya teach, מפיה ומשוליה לא יביא ואם הביא כשר?
mipeha umishuleha lo yavi ve'im heivi kasher? Same point, לכתחילה lechatchila that's
not ideal for the altar, but
בדיעבד bedieved it's acceptable,
and since בדיעבד bedieved it's acceptable for the altar, then לכתחילה lechatchila
it's even good for us. Okay? So now the גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay, so where were we? Okay. ואם הביא כשר. Ve'im heivi kasher.
ואלא למעוטי יין כושי? Ve'ela lema'utei yayin kushi? So here's a whole
list of things. Wine that is black. בורק, Borak, wine that's very
light or white. Presumably, it does not mean
from the white grapes, from the green grapes. Presumably, it means that
it's turned white.
הליסטון, Hiliston, which the רשב\"ם Rashbam says means a very type of
a sweet wine, like that they'd added stuff to it or maybe
it's unnaturally sweet. It's like the stuff like people joke, right, like
Manischewitz. Anybody who really likes wine, who considers Manischewitz wine? It's some
type of a grape drink, it's not
wine. What?
It's produced by hanging the grapes in the sun.
Ah, so the sun sweetens it.
Greek word helios.
Oh, Helios! Oh, nice. Because what the sun
does... greater sugar content. Thank you. That's good. That's good to know.
Okay.
שמרתף Shemartef of your wine cellar because you'll remember before the משנה
Mishnah finally some relationship with the משנה Mishnah but when you sell
stuff in the wine cellar a certain percentage can be this יין
קוסס. Yayin Koses. יין קוסס Yayin Koses is wine that's beginning to
sour. So שמרתף Shemartef here
means average wines from the cellar which has a chance of being,
of that there's some of it that's beginning to sour. Okay. ושצמוקים
Ve-she-tzimukim or raisin wine. So maybe all of those בדיעבד Bedi'avad would
be not good. Those are really considered to
be B-quality, C-quality wine and even בדיעבד Bedi'avad no good on the
מזבח. Mizbe'ach. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute. והתניא בכולם לא
יביא ואם הביא כשר. Ve-hatanya bekulam lo yavi ve-im hevi kasher. Once
again, we got a ברייתא Braita that says no, בדיעבד Bedi'avad it's
good, and if it's בדיעבד Bedi'avad it's good, we're not going to
disallow it for קידוש. Kiddush. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay. אלא
לאתויי יין קוסס. Ela le-atuyei yayin koses.
Fine. How about this? How about wine that's not just maybe souring,
but definitely souring? Okay, remember that was what we've been discussing until
now. It smells vinegary, it's definitely sour. מזוג, Mazug,
now this is going to be very interesting. Mixed wine, mixed with
water as which as we know they would regularly do, three to
one ratio or something. But on the מזבח Mizbe'ach it has to
be pure unmixed wine. Okay, so for the מזבח Mizbe'ach at least
that's clearly no good.
In the ספרי Sifrei they learn it from ונסכו רביעית ההין יין.
Ve-nisko revi'it ha-hin yayin. The entire רביעית ההין revi'it ha-hin has to
be all wine, not wine plus water. Okay, so that would not
be so any mixed wine mixed with water is not good on
the מזבח. Mizbe'ach. Okay. מגולה, Megulah, if it is left exposed because
then there's a fear that it became poisoned by a snake in
the גמרא. Gemara. וששל שמרים, Ve-she-shel shemarim, this שמרים Shemarim is what
we've been talking about, you take, you took the lees, you added
water which we knew wasn't even considered wine at all, was considered
winey water, it was basically water. ושיריחו רע. Ve-she-reicho ra. And ריחו
רע reicho ra is apparently different than קוסס. Koses. קוסס Koses is
like it's vinegary smell, it's starting to sour. ריחו רע reicho ra
means like it's really has like an off taste, not necessarily about
beginning to maybe turn to vinegar, but it's an off taste. So
in all of those, or off smell. Smell, thank you. Smell. Okay.
דתניא בכולם, De-tanya bekulam, and those we know are all בדיעבד Bedi'avad
no good. בכולם לא יביא ואם הביא פסול. Bekulam lo yavi ve-im
hevi pasul. So those that are no good בדיעבד, Bedi'avad, presumably those
would all not be acceptable for קידוש. Kiddush. But we've got a
problem that the principle doesn't work, because some of these things are
definitely okay for קידוש. Kiddush. Let's take a look. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this.
לאתויי מאי? Le-atuyei mai? So fine, you've got your list now of
things that are not good for wine on the מזבח. Mizbe'ach. Which
of these do you want to exclude for קידוש? Kiddush? אי לאתויי
קוסס, Ei le-atuyei koses, if it's the whole issue about the souring
wine, פלוגתא דרבי יוחנן ורבי יהושע בן לוי. Plogta de-Rabbi Yochanan ve-Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi. That's the debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and
רבי יהושע בן לוי, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, you might remember, when
it starts smelling like vinegar, is it still considered wine or is
it considered vinegar? Now, it is not clear exactly what's bothering the
גמרא. Gemara. This seems to be a perfect answer. Let's say we're
adopting the position of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that it's halachically still
wine, but because it is starting to smell like vinegar, it's not
acceptable for the מזבח, Mizbe'ach, therefore not acceptable for קידוש. Kiddush. This
seems like a perfect example. Technically it's wine, that's רבי יוחנן's Rabbi
Yochanan's position, but it's not good for קידוש Kiddush and not good
for the מזבח. Mizbe'ach. So I don't, it's not clear to me
and the רשב"ם Rashbam tries to explain it, but somehow the גמרא
Gemara assumes that since רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says it's יין, Yayin,
that would mean he would accept it even for קידוש. Kiddush. I
don't know how we know that. Anyway, אי לאתויי מזוג, Ei le-atuyei
mazug,
if we're talking about mixed with water, עלויי מעלי. Illuyei ma'ali.
So what do you mean? For us, for קידוש, Kiddush, for the
מזבח Mizbe'ach it has to be all wine, but for us, the
ideal is to be mixed with water. Real wine for human consumption
is considered this wine mixed with water, at least that's what it
was in the גמרא. Gemara. עלויי מעלי, Illuyei ma'ali, דאמר רב יוסי
ברבי חנינא מודים חכמים לרבי אליעזר בכוס של ברכה שאין מברכין עליו
עד שיתנו לתוכו מים. De-amar Rav Yossi be-Rabbi Chanina modim Chachamim le-Rabbi
Eliezer bekos shel berachah she-ein mevarachin alav ad she-yitnu letocho mayim. So
there's a debate between רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and the חכמים Chachamim
if you drink raw wine without, that's what it's called חי, Chai,
raw wine without the water, again because they would always mix it
with water, would you still make בורא פרי הגפן? Borei pri ha-gefen
Maybe since nobody drinks it straight, you don't make בורא פרי הגפן.
Borei Pri HaGafen So that was the debate.
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says you can only make
בורא פרי הגפן Borei Pri HaGafen if it's mixed, and the חכמים
Chachamim say you can even make בורא פרי הגפן Borei Pri HaGafen.
even if it's raw. But the חכמים Chachamim agree to רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer that when it comes not to בורא פרי הגפן Borei
Pri HaGafen, but to קידוש. Kiddush. And for קידוש, Kiddush, everybody agrees,
whether you can make
בורא פרי הגפן Borei Pri HaGafen, when it’s raw, everybody agrees for
קידוש, Kiddush, it’s only mixed wine, okay, that seems to be, right?
דחכמים מודים לרבי אליעזר בכוס של ברכה שאין מברכין עליו עד שיתן
לתוכו מים. DeChachamim modim l'Rabbi Eliezer bekos shel beracha she'ein mevarachin alav
ad sheyitein letocho mayim. Now
of course that raises an interesting question. How do we make קידוש
Kiddush on stuff that is like pure, you know, pure grapes, fermented
grape juice, no water added? So it seems like some of this
has to do with, you know, societal context and what we the
society considers to be wine or not. I’m going to get to
that in a minute about that, but that’s fascinating. But anyway, even
if we don’t say so, it’s certainly true that mixed with water
is not פסול pasul for קידוש. Kiddush. It sounds like it’s required
for קידוש, Kiddush, let alone not פסול. pasul. So clearly we cannot
be saying that that’s what we learn from wine on the altar.
Here we, here it’s definitely an improvement. Okay. אילימא למעוטי מגולה. Ilima
lema'utei megulah.
Now if you say that we’re talking about exposed wine and therefore
there’s a concern that it might be poisoned and therefore you can’t
use it because of the comparison to the altar, סכנה היא. sakanah
hi.
You don’t need a comparison to the altar to say don’t use
it. You don’t need to say don’t use it for קידוש. Kiddush.
It’s אסור assur to drink it, סתם. stam It’s a, you know,
it’s a life risk. Okay. אילימא למעוטי שושמרים. Ilima lema'utei shoshmarim. Okay,
so fine, so maybe what we’re doing is we’re excluding this case
of תמד, temed, the winy water, you know, that you added to
the, the water you added to the lees. That you can’t use
for קידוש. Kiddush. היכי דמי? Heichi dami? So what’s the case? Why
do we need the comparison to the altar wine? אי דרמי תלתא
ואתא ארבעה, Ei darmi tlata v'ata arba'ah, if you put in three
units and took out four, so חמרא מעליא הוא chamra ma'alya hu
and that’s real wine. So then and it’s classic wine, grape juice,
you know, the juice and the water and whatever, and of course
you can make not only בורא פרי הגפן Borei Pri HaGafen but
make קידוש Kiddush on it. Okay. אי דרמי תלתא ואתא תלתא ופלגא,
Ei darmi tlata v'ata tlata u'palga, you put in three and took
out three and a half, תנא דרבנן ודאחרים היא, tanna d'Rabbanan v'd'Acherim
hi,
that’s the debate. The Rabbis say that’s just winy water, אחרים Acherim
say it’s wine, so according to the Rabbis of course you can’t
use it and you don’t need to make the comparison to the
altar, and according to אחרים Acherim it’s wine and of course you
can use it. אלא למעוטי, Ella lema'utei, so therefore there’s no case
there that it would be wine but not usable for the קידוש.
Kiddush. Either it’s wine and usable for קידוש, Kiddush, if it’s got
enough grape juice content in it, or it’s not wine at all,
it’s just water, so you don’t even make בורא פרי הגפן. Borei
Pri HaGafen, So there’s no case in the middle there. So far
the best candidate, which I still don’t know why the גמרא Gemara
rejected, was the wine that’s beginning to sour. That’s like a perfect
case of it’s still wine, you make a בורא פרי הגפן, Borei
Pri HaGafen. but you can’t use it for קידוש. Kiddush. But for
whatever reason the גמרא Gemara rejected it. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this, אלא למעוטי שריחו רע. Ella lema'utei shereiacho ra. Fine, we’re
going to exclude the wine that smells bad. That wine is still
הלכתית halachically בורא פרי הגפן, Borei Pri HaGafen but it’s invalid for
the altar and therefore it’s invalid for קידוש. Kiddush. So I really
don’t understand the difference between ריחו רע reiacho ra and ריחו חומץ,
reiacho chometz, which is what the גמרא Gemara before called כוסס, koses,
right? Whether it’s a bad smell or a vinegary smell, I would
think vinegary smell would be worse because it’s in the process of
becoming vinegar, right? So but anyway, all right, but that’s the basic
point. Something that’s still בורא פרי הגפן Borei Pri HaGafen but is
not really a, just a-grade wine, but you know is like a
C-grade or a D-grade wine, even though it’s בורא פרי הגפן, Borei
Pri HaGafen you know, you can’t make קידוש Kiddush on it, which
would raise the question for everybody who’s always made קידוש Kiddush on
Manischewitz wine. But again the גמרא Gemara said super sweet is still
in the, is in the B category, not in the D. The
D is not just that it’s like too, not that it’s whatever,
not subtle or sophisticated, the D category is that it’s really bad
smell. That, but it’s still enough to make בורא פרי הגפן. Borei
Pri HaGafen. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, ואיבעית אימא
למעוטי
מגולה, V'iba'is eima lema'utei megulah, or you could say we’re coming to
exclude the wine that was exposed and maybe a snake drank from
it. So ah, you can’t even drink that, you know, under normal
cases. ואף על גב דעבריה במיסננת, V'af al gav d'avreih b'misanenet, but
we’re talking about that you passed it through a sieve, and therefore
the sieve would get out the, the poison. So הלכתית halachically it
would be מותר mutar to drink, but since it’s wine that might
have been poisoned and had the poison removed, it’s not a, it’s
still invalid for the altar. And since it’s still invalid for the
altar, therefore it is invalid for
קידוש. Kiddush. כרב נחמיה, Ke'Rav Nechemia, like רב נחמיה Rav Nechemia says
that you’re allowed to do that and drink it, and even though
you’re allowed to drink it, הקריבהו hakrivehu נא na
לפחתך, lefachatecha would you bring this to your officer, to, to the
governor? הירצך hayirtzecha או o הישא hayissa פניך? panecha, Would this find
how, you know, have him find favor in your, would you find
favor in his eyes as a result of this? So this is
not something that, it’s still yucky, and you wouldn’t bring this, you
know, to, on the altar, and therefore it’s פסול pasul even בדיעבד,
b'diavad, and therefore you can’t use it for קידוש Kiddush wine.
One last thing about this and then I want to take a
step back and discuss some of the other practical implications, because right
now the only thing we’ve excluded is bad smell. wine. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, last point though, בעי רמי בר כהנא
*ba'ei Remi bar Kahana* חמוה דרב משרשיא מרבא *chamua d'Rav Mesharshiya me'Rava*.
רב כהנא *Rav Kahana*, the father-in-law of רב משרשיא *Rav Mesharshiya*, asked
רבא *Rava*, חמר חיוריין מהו *chamar chivaryan mahu*? What about white wine?
Now the question is, didn't he learn the ברייתא *baraita* before? The
ברייתא *baraita* before said white wine לכתחילה l'chatchila, *lechatchila* no good, בדיעבד
b'diavad *bedieved* it's okay for the altar. So some say that he's
talking about maybe it's really, really pale, it's changed a great degree,
it's not exactly—anyway, and what's his answer? אמר ליה *amar lei*, אל
תרא יין כי יתאדם *al tere yayan ki yit'adam*. Do not be
drawn after wine because it is ruddy, but what that פסוק *pasuk*
shows is that wine, paradigmatic wine is red. Okay, so what are
you saying? So if you look at the רשב״ם *Rashbam*, the רשב״ם
*Rashbam* has two explanations of what the conclusion of this is. He
says, אניראה בעיני *anireh
be'einai*, it's the third line down in the wide lines, דהיינו *de'hainu*,
הנהו *hanehu*, I'm sorry,
no, four lines down excuse me in the wide lines, אלמא יין
אדום קודם לנסכים דשכר כתיב ביה *alma yayan adom kodem l'nesachim de'shachar
ktiv bei*. So he says that you see that it should be
preferable. I'm sorry, wait, where was the line I wanted to get?
Excuse me, one minute.
No, but there was some—oh no, I'm sorry, two lines from the
top where he says חמר חיוריין מהו *chamar chivaryan mahu*. Two lines
from the wide lines, middle of the line, לנסכים *l'nesachim*. ויש מפרשים
לקדוש ולא נהירא *v'yesh mefarshim l'kiddush v'lo nehera*. So he says the
question is can you use it as a—on the altar? And then
the question was, you know, no, maybe if it's a little bit
white you can't לכתחילה l'chatchila, *lechatchila*, maybe if it's too white you
can't even בדיעבד *bedieved*. Okay, but that was a question of the
altar. He says some say the question is can you use it
for קידוש Kiddush, *Kiddush*? And then he says but I don't think
that's correct, לא נהירא *lo nehera*. But what it reflects is a
possibility that you could have read the conclusion of the גמרא Gemara?
*Gemara* that even though earlier the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* said that white
wine or maybe wine that was a little bit off-colored is כשר
*kasher* for קידוש Kiddush. *Kiddush*, maybe wine that is like really white
and maybe, you know, wine that's made from like a different type
of grapes that's really white or who knows, or that's faint color
a lot, maybe this is saying that would be פסול *pasul*, you'd
have to use red wine for קידוש Kiddush *Kiddush*. Now, it's a
way of reading the end of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. The רשב״ם
*Rashbam* says we're talking only about נסכים *nesachim*, but that's a way
of reading it. So but what the clearly—the only thing that one
thing that is clearly excluded is this issue of bad smell. Now,
let's talk about some practical implications because this is really interesting. Number
one, I've been talking about grape juice. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* discussed
before wine you squeezed even day-old wine, you know, one day or
one minute from the grapes, it still could be used. But how
about stuff that can't ferment? So if you take a look at
the רשב״ם *Rashbam* earlier where the רשב״ם *Rashbam* says, let me find
it for you,
he somewhere explicitly discusses that.
Okay, yeah, you see יין כוסס *yayan koses*, it's about ten lines
down in the narrow lines, that's the wine that's beginning to become
vinegar. So he says הוא יין הנמכר בחנות ופסול הוא *hu yayan
hanimkar b'chanut u'pasul hu*. So why is it פסול *pasul*? He doesn't
say just because it is bad-smelling or whatever, right? Because you have
to be—הוא דלא הוי שכרא ולא ראוי להיות שכרא *hu d'lo havi
shechara v'lo ra'ui l'hiyot shechara*. Because it is not intoxicating and it's
not fit to ever become intoxicating. כי יין מגיתו דסופו מיהא להיות
שכרא *ki yayan migito de'sofo mei'ha l'hiyot shechara*. As opposed to day-old
wine that is unfermented but eventually could be, could ferment. So he
makes a distinction between wine that's not possible to ferment and wine
that could ferment. Now, in the end the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
that, you know, יין כוסס *yayan koses* might be כשר *kasher* for
קידוש Kiddush *Kiddush*. But at least in theory he puts out right—if
you remember that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* said, oh, יין כוסס
*yayan koses* if it's יין *yayan* it's כשר *kasher* for קידוש Kiddush
*Kiddush*. So you could say the opposite. The conclusion, even though he
makes the conceptual distinction, maybe the conclusion is the same way יין
כוסס *yayan koses* could be used for קידוש Kiddush. *Kiddush* if you
call it wine, maybe grape juice you could use for קידוש Kiddush.
*Kiddush* if you call it wine. But at least it shows you
that there's a question here whether we can call this stuff wine
or not. So that is the question
about grape juice. Grape juice is not the same as day-old unfermented
wine. Grape juice the way we make it, we take out various
chemicals, we pasteurize it whatever, we treat it in a way in
which it can never ferment. Now, some disagree and say
even if it could never ferment, it still is wine. Others will
say no, well, as soon as it came out of the grape,
it was this day-old unfermented wine and therefore got the halakhic status
of wine and even if now you treat it and make it
unable to ferment, it still retains that same halakhic status. Okay, I
don't know, but anyway, but that's the questions around grape juice. In
Israel, I think you see this stuff that says מיץ ענבים טבעי
*mitz anavim tiv'i*. Have you ever seen those barrels? And I always
thought, what do you mean every מיץ ענבים *mitz anavim* is טבעי
*tiv'i*? What? But I think what it is—so I was doing a
little reading about this last night—is that... That is unfermented wine. They
do not heat that. That that is exactly to address this issue,
that that's grape juice that they come straight out of the grape,
and they basically I don't think they expose it to air. I
think they do it in a like an airtight type of a
process, you know? It gets pressed, it goes through pipes, it gets
sealed, whatever. It doesn't get exposed to air because if it gets
exposed to air it'll start to ferment and that actually is completely
untreated grape juice. And that would be exactly this case of the
day-old grape juice, you know, day-old unfermented grape juice that is כשר.
But the type of thing that we have as grape juice which
we treat in whatever, that's the matters of debate. So I personally
like, you know, some people say you don't even make בורא פרי
הגפן Borei Pri HaGafen. on it, by the way. I'm serious, grape,
you know, our grape juice. So as I said, I personally try
to be מקפיד makpid particularly Friday night. שבת Shabbos day is more
מקל meikil because שבת Shabbos day is the, you know, it's easier
to use like, you know, what do you call
it, חמר מדינה. chamar medinah. But Friday night where there is a
particular הקפדה hakpada on wine and so on, that being said, as
I mentioned the other day, we should always be very careful to
have a grape juice option because there are people dealing with alcoholism
and so on, and it's a, you know, even a little bit
of wine is a very non-trivial thing. Shully, you wanted to say
something?
In the ירושלמי תרומות Yerushalmi Terumot there's actually discussion of whether you
can take תרומה terumah from vinegar for wine and they conclude that
בדיעבד it actually works.
Right, so that is a question too, but that doesn't mean it's
called wine. They don't call it wine. It might be different standards.
Right. So that's one issue. I want, yes?
You mentioned about the quality of the wine and having to be
fermented, but what about the requirement of intoxication? In terms of if
it's going to be used on the מזבח mizbe'ach it has to
be able to intoxicate.
But eventually. It doesn't have to yet be fermented. It has to
be fermentable. But לכתחילה, l'chatchila לכתחילה, lechatchila right, right,
right. So לכתחילה it has to already be fermented. I don't know
if there's a specific alcohol content that is required. So that's one
issue. One issue is the grape juice issue. Another issue if you
turn back to תוספות Tosafot on the עמוד א, amud aleph, okay,
ויאמר למעוטי יין מגתו. vayomer l'mi'utei yayin mi-gito.
תוספות Tosafot says the following: אין להוכיח מכאן דיין מבושל כשר לקידוש
ומברכין עליו בורא פרי הגפן. ain lo hochi'ach mikan d'yayin mevushal kasher
l'Kiddush u-mevarchin alav Borei Pri HaGafen.
So we were talking about do you make a בורא פרי הגפן
Borei Pri HaGafen on grape juice. תוספות Tosafot wants to know do
you make a בורא פרי הגפן Borei Pri HaGafen, on יין מבושל,
yayin mevushal, okay, which is like 90 percent of kosher wine, okay.
Maybe you don't even make a בורא פרי הגפן. Borei Pri HaGafen.
Maybe you can't use it for קידוש, okay, because maybe if you
can't, you know, is that still, now why? Not just the question
of can you use it on the altar. Remember yesterday we discussed,
does something retain the ברכה bracha if you if you degrade its
quality? Okay, if you're, so he says במבשל be-mevashel it is degrading
its quality, so maybe it should lose the ברכה bracha of
בורא פרי הגפן. Borei Pri HaGafen Okay. So, מברכין עליו בורא פרי
הגפן מדלא קאמר למעוטי יין מבושל. mevarchin alav Borei Pri HaGafen mi-d'lo
ka-amar l'mi'utei yayin mevushal. Why didn't they say, oh, they kind of
excluded יין מבושל, yayin mevushal, so that proves since they didn't, implicitly
יין מבושל yayin mevushal is okay for קידוש. He says דלאו ראיה
היא דאפילו אין מקדשין עליו לא מצי למימר למעוטי יין מבושל דאם
כן הוה ליה למימר אין מברכין עליו בורא פרי הגפן. d'lav reaya
hee d'afilu ain m'kadshein alav lo matzi l'meimar l'mi'utei yayin mevushal d'im
ken hava lei l'meimar ain m'varchin alav Borei Pri HaGafen. So he
says you can't prove from here that יין מבושל yayin mevushal is
okay because they didn't say, oh, the point is to exclude יין
מבושל. yayin mevushal. Maybe the reason they didn't say it is because
maybe the גמרא felt that יין מבושל yayin mevushal you don't even
make בורא פרי הגפן Borei Peri HaGafen. on it, so didn't have
to exclude יין מבושל yayin mevushal because you don't even make בורא
borei פרי pri הגפן, hagafen, it's not even wine, you don't make
בורא borei פרי pri הגפן. hagafen Okay, but then he says, okay,
he says אבל aval he says יש להביא ראיה מירושלמי דשקלים דיין
גמור הוא, yesh l'havi reaya m'Yerushalmi de-Shekalim d'yayin gamur hu, okay, and
then he's
and then he brings a proof that יין מבושל yayin mevushal is
יין גמור yayin gamur and you make בורא borei פרי pri הגפן
hagafen and you're able to make קידוש on it. But that's an
interesting question, יין מבושל, yayin mevushal, can you make קידוש on it?
Okay, so let me now read you רמבם Rambam because רמבם Rambam
is the classic position that is the most מחמיר machmir for what
you need to have for wine for קידוש on for קידוש. And
here's what the רמבם Rambam says in כט יד: kaf-tet yod-dalet: אין
מקדשין אלא על יין הראוי לנסך אגב המזבח. Ain m'kadshein ella al
yayin ha-rauy l'nasech agav ha-mizbe'ach. ולפיכך
אם נתערב בו דבש או שאור אפילו כטיפת חרדל בחבית גדולה,
Ve-fikach im nitarev bo d'vash o se'or
afilu k'tipat chardal b'chavit gedola, if there is even the tiniest of
extraneous sort of things added to it, even one drop in a
huge
barrel, אין מקדשין עליו. ain m'kadshein alav. So according to the רמבם,
Rambam, what?
Those are two things that are not allowed on the מזבח.
mizbe'ach. Ah, right. That's true. So you're right, it's not just extraneous.
שאור se'or and דבש d'vash are not allowed on the מזבח. mizbe'ach.
That is an excellent point. You're right. I was automatically translating it
the way some אחרונים acharonim do, but I think you're completely correct.
The רמבם Rambam meant specifically because those don't go on the מזבח.
mizbe'ach. Some אחרונים acharonim though want to read the רמבם Rambam that
any additive פוסל pasuls the wine, okay. And that's how some אחרונים
acharonim want to read it. But Dov I think is a hundred
percent correct that the פשט p'shat of
the רמבם, Rambam, what? פרק כט הלכה יד. Perek kaf-tet halacha yod-dalet.
כך אנו מורין בכל המערב.
Kach anu
morin b'chol ha-ma'arav.
Okay, in the entire West. And יש מי yesh mi madod the
ability to say כך אנו מורין בכל המערב. Kach anu morin b'chol
ha-ma'arav. I mean you, רמבם, Rambam, say something and everybody in the
entire Western, you know, world listens to it. Anyway.
But he didn't know it was the מערב.
Ma'arav. Well, at this point he did know that. ויש מי שמתיר
לקדש עליו ואומר לא נאמר היין ראוי לנסך על גבי המזבח אלא
להוציא יין שריחו רע או מגולה
או מבושל. Ve-yesh mi she-matir le-kadesh alav ve-omer lo ne'emar ha-yayin ra'uy
le-nasech al gabei ha-mizbe'ach ela le-hotzi yayin she-reicho ra o meguleh o
mevushal. Then you have those types of things, that's okay, you add
a little honey, you add whatever. The only thing we're excluding, there
is what's clearly excluded is bad smelling, or exposed with the snakish,
or מבושל, mevushal, okay? שאין מקדשין על אחד מהם. She-ein mekadeshin al
echad mei-hem.
But this thing of adding a little דבש, dvash, that's okay. What
emerges from the רמב״ם Rambam is even the more lenient position that
the רמב״ם Rambam just expressed would still say that מבושל mevushal would
not be acceptable for קידוש. Okay? And the ראב״ד Ra'avad agrees with
this second position, okay, that you can add things, sweeteners and honey
and whatever, okay, but still the רמב״ם Rambam basically says you cannot
use מבושל. mevushal. And as I think if I remember correctly, that's
the פסק psak of the שולחן ערוך. Shulchan Aruch. Let me just
check very quickly.
Okay,
so, it's in רע״ב Reish Ayin Bet in שולחן ערוך, Shulchan Aruch,
and then I want to say,
so
he says by the way you can make it on raw wine,
which is what we always do. Oh, מקדשין על יין מבושל ועל
יין שיש בו דבש, Mekadeshin al yayin mevushal ve-al yayin she-yesh bo
dvash, so he פסקן-ed pasken against the רמב״ם. Rambam. And then he
says ויש אומרים שאין מקדשין עליהם. Ve-yesh omrim she-ein mekadeshin alei-hem. And
the רמ״א Rama says והמנהג לקדש עליו אפילו יש לו יין אחר.
Ve-ha-minhag le-kadesh alav afillu yesh lo yayin acher. Okay, and then so
that's that. Then there's also a whole discussion about the red wine,
is red wine לכתחילה based on the last line of the גמרא?
The last thing I want to say about this, because Eli's been
bringing it up, is the issue about מזוג. mazug. So right, from
the גמרא it might sound like unmixed wine you couldn't use. But
of course we know that's all of our wine and you have
to say standards have changed about that. But Eli's been bringing up
the question about
what's fine, at what stage is it so watered down that it's
no good. All the גמרא we've been learning seems to be three
to one, it's still wine, but more than three to one seems
very clear from the גמרא is no longer wine. The whole case
of הצימד והחמיץ, ha-tzimid ve-he-chamitz,
yeah, but that's because even in הצימד והחמיץ ha-tzimid ve-he-chamitz because you
assumed that more from water was left behind and more grape juice
came out. But everybody assumed you needed the three to one ratio
and less than three to one assumed would be water and not
wine. So then Eli's been saying but the אשכנזים Ashkenazim say six
to one. And he's right, the רמ״א Rama says six to one
in these הלכות, halachot, not in this הלכה, halacha, in הלכות halachot
of בורא borei פרי pri הגפן.
hagafen Okay, so six water to one of wine.
So the question is like where does he get it from? So
I was actually researching this last night and the ערוך השולחן Aruch
HaShulchan says I don't understand where you're getting this from! The גמרא
says three to one! Where is he getting six to one? So
he says it's maybe he gets it from laws of סתם יינם.
stam yeinam סתם stam יינם yeinam, is actually an interesting הלכה halacha
that if you mix סתם stam. יינם yeinam with like some with
a liquid, it's actually בטל batel in six, you don't need sixty.
Normally you need sixty for ביטול, bittul, here you only need six.
So he said that seems like it's sort of saying that six
in a liquid, when it's still one to six, is still enough
to be significant. So he thinks that the רמ״א Rama learned it
from there and that thought that it's somewhat societally dependent. What do
we consider to be wine might depend on the society. So in
societies in which a six to one ratio is still considered wine,
which maybe was the רמ״א's Rama situation, that's where he's getting it
from. But the point is, yes, the גמרא makes it sound very
clear that anything more than three to one is no longer wine,
but the רמ״א Rama actually rules six to one. Okay, we'll end
with this.